<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" ".//reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<!-- WK: Set category, IPR, docName -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-wkumari-opsawg-sdi-04" ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <!-- WK: Set long title. -->

    <title abbrev="template">Secure Device Install</title>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Colin Doyle" initials="C." surname="Doyle">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1133 Innovation Way</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale, CA</city>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>cdoyle@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="31" month="May" year="2019"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>Deploying a new network device often requires that an employee
      physically travel to a datacenter to perform the initial install and
      configuration, even in shared datacenters with "smart-hands" type
      support. In many cases, this could be avoided if there were a standard,
      secure way to initially provision the devices.</t>

      <t>This document extends existing auto-install / Zero-Touch Provisioning
      to make the process more secure.</t>

      <t>[ Ed note: Text inside square brackets ([]) is additional background
      information, answers to frequently asked questions, general musings,
      etc. They will be removed before publication. This document is being
      collaborated on in Github at:
      https://github.com/wkumari/draft-wkumari-opsawg-sdi. The most recent
      version of the document, open issues, etc should all be available here.
      The authors (gratefully) accept pull requests. ]</t>

      <t>[ Ed note: This document introduces concepts and serves as the basic
      for discussion - because of this, it is conversational, and would need
      to be firmed up before being published ]</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In a growing, global network, significant amounts of time and money
      are spent simply deploying new devices and "forklift" upgrading existing
      devices. In many cases, these devices are in shared datacenters (for
      example, Internet Exchange Points (IXP) or "carrier neutral
      datacenters"), which have staff on hand that can be contracted to
      perform tasks including physical installs, device reboots, loading
      initial configurations, etc. There are also a number of (often vendor
      proprietary) protocols to perform initial device installs and
      configurations - for example, many network devices will attempt to use
      DHCP to get an IP address and configuration server, and then fetch and
      install a configuration when they are first powered on.</t>

      <t>Network device configurations contain a significant amount of
      security related and / or proprietary information (for example, RADIUS
      or TACACS+ secrets). Exposing these to a third party to load onto a new
      device (or using an auto-install techniques which fetch an (unencrypted)
      config file via something like TFTP) is simply not acceptable to many
      operators, and so they have to send employees to remote locations to
      perform the initial configuration work. As well as having a significant
      monetary cost, it also takes significantly longer to install devices and
      is generally inefficient.</t>

      <t>There are some workarounds to this, such as asking the vendor to
      pre-configure the devices before shipping it; asking the smart-hands to
      install a terminal server; providing a minimal, unsecured configuration
      and using that to bootstrap to a complete configuration, etc; but these
      are often clumsy and have security issues - for example, in the terminal
      server case, the console port connection could be easily snooped.</t>

      <t>This document layers security onto existing auto-install solutions to
      provide a secure method to initially configure new devices. It is
      optimized for simplicity, both for the implementor and the operator; it
      is explicitly not intended to be an "all singing, all dancing" fully
      featured system for managing installed / deployed devices, nor is it
      intended to solve all use-cases - rather it is a simple targeted
      solution to solve a common operational issue. Solutions such as <xref
      target="RFC8572">Secure Zero Touch Provisioning (SZTP)"</xref> are much
      more fully featured, but also more complex to implement and / or are not
      widely deployed yet. </t>

      <section title="Requirements notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview / Example Scenario">
      <t>Sirius Cybernetics Corp needs another peering router, and so they
      order another router from Acme Network Widgets, to be drop-shipped to a
      POP. Acme begins assembling the new device, and tells Sirius what the
      new device's serial number will be (SN:17894321). When Acme first
      installs the firmware on the device and boots it, the device generates a
      public-private keypair, and Acme publishes it on their keyserver (in a
      certificate, for ease of use).</t>

      <t>While Acme is shipping the new device, Sirius begins generating the
      initial device configuration. Once the config is ready, Sirius contacts
      the Acme keyserver, provides the serial number of the new device and
      fetches the device's public key. Sirius then encrypts the device
      configuration and puts this encrypted config on a (local) TFTP
      server.</t>

      <t>When the POP receives the new device, they install it in Sirius'
      rack, and connect the cables as instructed. The new device powers up and
      discovers that it has not yet been configured. It enters its autoboot
      state, and begins DHCPing. Sirius' DHCP server provides it with an IP
      address and the address of the configuration server. The router uses
      TFTP to fetch a file named according to its serial number
      (acme_17894321.cfg). It then uses its private key to decrypt this file,
      and, assuming it validates, installs the new configuration.</t>

      <t>Only the "correct" device will have the required private key and be
      able to decrypt and use the config file (See Security Considerations).
      An attacker would be able to connect to the network and get an IP
      address. They would also be able to retrieve (encrypted) config files by
      guessing serial numbers (or perhaps the server would allow directory
      listing), but without the private keys an attacker will not be able to
      decrypt the files.</t>

      <t>This document uses the serial number of the device as a unique
      identifier for simplicity; some vendors may not want to implement the
      system using the serial number as the identifier for business reasons (a
      competitor or similar could enumerate the serial numbers and determine
      how many devices have been manufactured). Implementors are free to
      choose some other way of generating identifiers (e.g UUID <xref
      target="RFC4122"/>), but this will likely make it somewhat harder for
      operators to use (the serial number is usually easy to find on a device,
      a more complex system is likely harder to track).</t>

      <t>[ Ed note: This example uses TFTP because that is what many vendors
      use in their auto-install / ZTP feature. It could easily instead be
      HTTP, FTP, etc. ]</t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section title="Vendor Role / Requirements ">
      <t>This section describes the vendors roles and responsibilities and
      provides an overview of what the device needs to do.</t>

      <section title="CA Infrastructure">
        <t>The vendor needs to run some (simple) CA infrastructure to sign and
        publish certificates. When a device is initially powered on (in the
        factory) it will generate a public / private keypair and a Certificate
        Signing Request (CSR), with the commonName being the serial number (or
        other unique token) of the device. The device sends this CSR to the
        CA, which signs the CSR and publishes the certificate on the
        certificate publication server. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Certificate Publication Server">
        <t>The certificate publication server contains a database of
        certificates. Customers (e.g Sirius Cybernetics Corp) query this
        server with the serial number (or other provided unique identifier) of
        a device, and retrieve the associated certificate. It is expected that
        operators will receive the unique identifier (serial number) of
        devices when they purchase them, and will download and store / cache
        the certificate. This means that there is not a hard requirement on
        the uptime / reachability of the certificate publication server.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="initial_cust_boot" title="Initial Customer Boot">
        <t>When the device is first booted by the customer (and on subsequent
        boots), if the device has no (valid) configuration file, it will
        perform standard an auto-install type functionality. For example, it
        will perform DHCP Discovery until it gets a DHCP offer including DHCP
        option 66 or 150. It will contact the server listed in these DHCP
        options and download its config file - note that this is existing
        functionality (for example, Cisco will fetch the config file named by
        the Bootfile-Name (DHCP option 67). </t>

        <t>After retrieving the config file, Secure Device Install devices
        will attempt to decrypt the configuration file using its private key.
        If it is able to decrypt and validate the file it will install the
        configuration, and start using it. Note that the device only needs to
        be able to reach get DHCP and download the config file - after the
        initial power-on in the factory,it does NOT need Internet access, it
        does not need to reach the CA or vendor, etc. </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Operator Role / Responsibilities">
      <section title="Administrative ">
        <t>When purchasing a new device, the accounting department will need
        to get the unique device identifier (likely serial number) of the new
        device and communicate it to the operations group.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Technical">
        <t>The operator will contact the vendor's publication server, and
        download the certificate (by providing the unique device identifier of
        the device). They will then encrypt the initial configuration to that
        key, and place it on the TFTP server. See Appendix B for examples.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Additional Considerations">
      <section title="Key storage">
        <t>Ideally, the keypair would be stored in a TPM on something which is
        identified as the &ldquo;router&rdquo; - for example, the chassis /
        backplane. This is so that a keypair is bound to what humans think of
        as the &ldquo;device&rdquo;, and not, for example, (redundant) routing
        engines. Devices which implement IEEE 802.1AR could choose to use the
        IDevID for this purpose. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Key replacement ">
        <t>It is anticipated that some operator may want to replace the
        (vendor provided) keys after installing the device. This would also
        allow for the use of certificates signed by the operator's CA (e.g
        using RFC7030 - Enrollment over Secure Transport) this is a trivial
        operation, but is not described here (to avoid cluttering up the doc).
        There are two options when implementing this - a vendor could allow
        the operator's key to completely replace the initial device generated
        key (which means that, if the device is ever sold, the new owner
        couldn't use this technique to install the device), or the device
        could prefer the operators installed key. This is an implementation
        decision left to the vendor.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Device reinstall">
        <t>Increasingly, operations is moving towards an automated model of
        device management, whereby portions (or the entire) configuration is
        programmatically generated. This means that operators may want to
        generate an entire configuration after the device has been initially
        installed and ask the device to load and use this new configuration.
        It is expected (but not defined in this document, as it is vendor
        specific) that vendors will allow the operator to copy a new,
        encrypted config (or part of a config) onto a device and then request
        that the device decrypt and install it (e.g: &lsquo;load replace
        &lt;filename&gt; encrypted)). If the operator has chosen to leave the
        original (vendor) keys on the device, they could also choose to reset
        the device to factory defaults, and allow the device to act as though
        it were the initial boot (see <xref target="initial_cust_boot"/>).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no requests of the IANA. </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This mechanism is intended to replace either expensive (traveling
      employees) or insecure mechanisms of installing newly deployed devices
      such as: unencrypted config files which can be downloaded by connecting
      to unprotected ports in datacenters, mailing initial config files on
      flash drives, or emailing config files and asking a third-party to copy
      and paste it over a serial terminal. It does not protect against devices
      with malicious firmware, nor theft and reuse of devices.</t>

      <t>An attacker (e.g a malicious datacenter employee) who has physical
      access to the device before it is connected to the network the attacker
      may be able to extract the device private key (especially if it isn't
      stored in a TPM), pretend to be the device when connecting to the
      network, and download and extract the (encrypted) config file. </t>

      <t>This mechanism does not really protect against a malicious vendor -
      while the keypair should be generated on the device, and the private key
      should be securely stored, we cannot detect or protect against a vendor
      who claims to do this, but instead generates the keypair off device and
      keeps a copy of the private key. It is largely understood in the
      operator community that a malicious vendor or attacker with physical
      access to the device is largely a "Game Over" situation. </t>

      <t>Even when using a secure bootstrapping mechanism, security conscious
      operators may wish to bootstrapping devices with a minimal / less
      sensitive config, and then replace this with a more complete one after
      install.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors wish to thank everyone who contributed, including Benoit
      Claise, Sam Ribeiro, Michael Richardson, Sean Turner and Kent Watsen.
      Joe Clarke provided significant comments and review.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-iana-objects-03.xml'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8572'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4122'?>
    </references>

    <section title="Changes / Author Notes.">
      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication ]</t>

      <t>From -00 to -01</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Nothing changed in the template!</t>
        </list>From -01 to -04:<list style="symbols">
          <t>See github commit log (AKA, we forgot to update this!)</t>

          <t>Added Colin Doyle.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -04 to -05:</t>

      <t>Addressed a number of comments received before / at IETF104 (Prague).
      These include:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Pointer to
          https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-netconf-zerotouch --
          included reference to (now) RFC8572 (KW)</t>

          <t>Suggested that 802.1AR IDevID (or similar) could be used. Stress
          that this is designed for simplicity (MR)</t>

          <t>Added text to explain that any unique device identifier can be
          used, not just serial number - serial number is simple and easy, but
          anything which is unique (and can be communicated to the customer)
          will work (BF).</t>

          <t>Lots of clarifications from Joe Clarke.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Demo / proof of concept">
      <t>This section contains a rough demo / proof of concept of the system.
      It is only intended for illustration; presumably things like algorithms,
      key lengths, format / containers will provide much fodder for
      discussion.</t>

      <t>It uses OpenSSL from the command line, in production something more
      automated would be used. In this example, the serial number of the
      router is SN19842256.</t>

      <section title="Step 1: Generating the certificate. ">
        <t>This step is performed by the router. It generates a key, then a
        csr, and then a self signed certificate.</t>

        <section title="Step 1.1: Generate the private key. ">
          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[$ openssl genrsa -out key.pem 2048
Generating RSA private key, 2048 bit long modulus
.................................................
.................................................
..........................+++
...................+++
e is 65537 (0x10001)
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Step 1.2: Generate the certificate signing request.">
          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[$ openssl req -new -key key.pem -out SN19842256.csr
Country Name (2 letter code) [AU]:.
State or Province Name (full name) [Some-State]:.
Locality Name (eg, city) []:.
Organization Name (eg, company) [Internet Widgits Pty Ltd]:.
Organizational Unit Name (eg, section) []:.
Common Name (e.g. server FQDN or YOUR name) []:SN19842256
Email Address []:.

Please enter the following 'extra' attributes
to be sent with your certificate request
A challenge password []:
An optional company name []:.

]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Step 1.3: Generate the (self signed) certificate itself. ">
          <t>$ openssl req -x509 -days 36500 -key key.pem -in SN19842256.csr
          -out SN19842256.crt</t>

          <t>The router then sends the key to the vendor&rsquo;s keyserver for
          publication (not shown).</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Step 2: Generating the encrypted config. ">
        <t>The operator now wants to deploy the new router.</t>

        <t>They generate the initial config (using whatever magic tool
        generates router configs!), fetch the router&rsquo;s certificate and
        encrypt the config file to that key. This is done by the operator.</t>

        <section title="Step 2.1: Fetch the certificate.">
          <t>$ wget http://keyserv.example.net/certificates/SN19842256.crt</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Step 2.2: Encrypt the config file. ">
          <t>I'm using S/MIME because it is simple to demonstrate. This is
          almost definitely not the best way to do this.<figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[$ openssl smime -encrypt -aes-256-cbc -in SN19842256.cfg\
  -out SN19842256.enc -outform PEM SN19842256.crt
$ more SN19842256.enc
-----BEGIN PKCS7-----
MIICigYJKoZIhvcNAQcDoIICezCCAncCAQAxggE+MIIBOgIBADAiMBUxEzARBgNV
BAMMClNOMTk4NDIyNTYCCQDJVuBlaTOb1DANBgkqhkiG9w0BAQEFAASCAQBABvM3
...
LZoq08jqlWhZZWhTKs4XPGHUdmnZRYIP8KXyEtHt
-----END PKCS7-----
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Step 2.3: Copy config to the config server.">
          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[$ scp SN19842256.enc config.example.com:/tftpboot
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Step 3: Decrypting and using the config. ">
        <t>When the router connects to the operator's network it will detect
        that does not have a valid configuration file, and will start the
        &ldquo;autoboot&rdquo; process. This is a well documented process, but
        the high level overview is that it will use DHCP to obtain an IP
        address and config server. It will then use TFTP to download a
        configuration file, based upon its serial number (this document
        modifies the solution to fetch an encrypted config file (ending in
        .enc)). It will then then decrypt the config file, and install it.</t>

        <t/>

        <section title="Step 3.1: Fetch encrypted config file from config server.">
          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[$ tftp 192.0.2.1 -c get SN19842256.enc
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Step 3.2: Decrypt and use the config. ">
          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[$ openssl smime -decrypt -in SN19842256.enc -inform pkcs7\
  -out config.cfg -inkey key.pem
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>If an attacker does not have the correct key, they will not be
          able to decrypt the config: <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[$ openssl smime -decrypt -in SN19842256.enc -inform pkcs7\
  -out config.cfg -inkey wrongkey.pem
Error decrypting PKCS#7 structure
140352450692760:error:06065064:digital envelope
 routines:EVP_DecryptFinal_ex:bad decrypt:evp_enc.c:592:
$ echo $?
4]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
